"Bystander"
Hey!
You wait right there!
Isn't this...?
Yeah... Not quite the
Queen I was expecting.
And it's only been two months
since she was crowned.
Seems like she's better
suited to run an orphanage.
Do you know what the
people are calling her?
The Cattle-Farming Goddess.
In a good way, of course.
So we've finally got a goddess among us.
At this rate, no one will remember
the chump who plugged up Trost, yeah?
One of the reasons Historia decided
to become queen was...
...to do all this.
This, meaning?
Taking care of the orphans and needy from
the underground to the edge of the walls.
Since he was raised underground,
the captain supported her, too.
When people need help,
she said she'll come to their rescue,
no matter who or where.
That's... what Historia wants to do.
Oh? You're slacking again!
Uh...
It's getting dark, you know!
She's becoming more
and more like my mother...
Some goddess...
I hear your hardening
experiments are going well.
Yeah...
But if we don't hurry... they'll be back.
What would you do?
If you met Reiner and Bertholdt...
and had to face them again?
I've got no other choice...
but to kill them.
I hope we find out soon.
About this world... and
why it is like it is.
All that we've done...
I don't want to regret any of it.
Even the kids from the underground
have been smiling lately.
This can't have been the wrong choice.
Yeah.
You've done great.
That's not...
Though you're the one who said
humanity should get wiped out.
Th-That was only 'cuz I got carried away!
What?
Gimme that.
Hey!
Eren's tired from the experiments.
That's true. Sorry, Mikasa.
Would you stop treating me
like some feeble old man?
Due to the military purge,
considerable talent was lost
from humanity's forces, but...
...the discovery of glowing
ore in the underground cavern
was one of many things gained.
Also, with Eren's hardening ability,
a certain anti-Titan weapon was born.
That's it...
Jam your head in here.
Now!
Ooh!
A direct hit on the nape!
This could be it...!
We did it! That's a 12-meter, crushed!
We did it!
Hell yeah! With this, we can kill Titans
without a single soldier fighting!
We'll hack down the
Titans all day and night!
Say hello to the executioner from hell!
We did it, Eren!
Eren?
He probably overused his Titan powers.
All he's done is hardening
experiments lately.
Sorry, Eren...
There's nothing to apologize for, Hange.
Who gives a damn if I'm tired?
Let's hurry... make
weapons, and get going...
...to Shiganshina.
We can win! We can beat 'em!
With the new weapons,
the Titans will crumble like paper!
You're so damn worked up.
Only you would be happy
about becoming a Scout.
That's right! Didn't Hitch try
to stop you from joining?
Hitch? Why would she?
Why? 'Cuz you two are... you know?
I don't follow, but...
Hitch told me off, saying I wasn't
cut out for it and not to act cool.
That if I stayed in the Military Police,
I could coast along in life.
I thought she was better than that...
Told her I was wrong about her.
- You shit.
- ...Huh?
- ...Marlo, are you stupid?
- He's a bowl cut imbecile.
Why? Marlo said nothing wrong.
Anyways, the only ones
as worked up as you are
the recruits with zero
battle experience.
Whoa, whoa... Think you're
some veteran hero now?
Compared to you, I am.
How rude. Weren't we in the 104th together?
Besides, we're not the only ones.
Everyone in the walls is pumped up
about the idea of retaking Wall Maria.
Is that so?
Still, you all do seem different now.
It's your faces, I guess...
What... exactly happened?
Wanna know?
No... I think... I'll ask later.
I'm outta here. See you later.
Eh? So soon?
Tomorrow's a prep day, so I'm heading
to my village in the morning.
Might find out something new there.
Good night.
Turning Conny's mom back to
normal... isn't impossible, right?
Yeah...
If our understanding of Titans
keeps improving, someday...
You're telling me Titans are people?
It's just speculation for now.
About 60 years.
It was like... I was stuck in a
nightmare that never would end.
A nightmare, huh?
Eh?
With all that's happened,
it's been so vague...
But who exactly are we fighting against?
That is, are Titans just...
...people being tormented
by some nightmare?
For a time, I was... one of those Titans.
Eren!
You still have bread and soup left.
Save talking for after you've eaten.
Right.
Sorry, Mikasa.
For crying out loud, Eren.
I swear that's all you do lately...
mumbling shit to yourself.
When you should be trying
to remember that one guy.
You saw, right? In the cavern
when those memories came back...
That guy in the Scouts
who you think met your dad.
Yeah... That day, I'm pretty sure
he was with my dad.
He's gotta know something.
The thing is, though, I feel like
I've met the guy somewhere.
You mean not Dr. Jaeger, but you, yourself?
I think so...
Smack your head and see if you remember.
That's right, twerp.
You might remember if you stopped
holding hands with Historia for once.
Get a head-butt from the commandant.
If that helped me remember, I'd...
Huh?
The Cadet Corps commandant...
Keith Sadies!
Before Erwin, he was the 12th
commander of the Scout Regiment.
It's been a long while since I've seen him.
Commandant Sadies.
What's wrong, Braus? Not sitting?
No! I am quite fine standing here!
If I recall...
Back in the day, I always used to
call you in here to chew you out.
And it's only been a handful of months.
I hardly recognize you all anymore.
Commander Sadies...
Rather, Commandant...
With preparations to retake
Wall Maria underway,
perhaps you can guess
what brings us here today.
Eren. You resemble your mother so much.
However, the fangs lurking deep
in your eyes are surely your father's.
Tell me about him! Everything you know!
I know nothing... in the
grand scheme of things.
However, I can tell you a story
utterly useless to humanity.
The story of my past...
as a mere bystander.
Twenty years ago. Wall Maria.
In front of the gates of
Shiganshina, he was there.
Hey, you!
What are you doing here?!
How did you get past the wall?!
Wh-What are all you doing
outside the wall?!
Don't tell me... you're fighting?!
Huh?
Was it the truth or a lie?
He couldn't remember why
he was outside the walls.
All of his memories had been lost.
Except that he knew his
name was Grisha Jaeger.
Who knew it's a crime to go into
Titan territory without permission?
I thought only you Scouts were
dumb enough to go outside the walls.
Isn't there a law that jails idiots
who drink on duty, Hannes?
Anyways, it's not like
he hurt anyone, so...
Let's not report it, all right?
Yeah.
Well?
What do you plan on doing
now, Grisha Jaeger?
I remember something other than my name.
I'm a doctor.
Introduce me to a hospital.
I should be able to help.
Oh?
Also... Do you think you could teach me?
About this world... About the Scouts.
About all of you.
He truly knew nothing at all.
Not about this world... or anything.
I see.
Although there's economic inequality,
there's peace within the walls.
At the least, you don't live
in constant fear of Titans.
That's good.
That's good, huh?
You're one of them?
Eh?
Within these cramped walls,
as long as there's food and alcohol,
some think that's good enough.
Not once have they stopped to
think how wide the world might be.
Is that why you venture outside the walls?
Is that what Scouts do?
That's right.
Does it seem foolish?
Not at all.
The Scouts are wiser and braver
than anyone else in the walls.
Your existence signifies
the freedom in our souls.
You're the pride of humanity.
Pride? We are?
Yes.
Come on, Keith.
Recruiting for the Scouts again, are we?
N-Not this time, Carla. I'm just...
Oh, no. I'd never be suited
for that kind of work.
Being a Scout takes someone special...
You have to be a chosen one.
Oh, is that right?
A chosen one...
It was the first time anyone told me that.
It's true, inside the wall was
much too cramped for me.
Another day, another defeat...
Will you ever build a
base outside the wall?
If only I was commander, I'd show results.
These idiots with their tiny brains...
I'd accomplish so much,
even they'd understand.
And then everyone...
would have to acknowledge me.
Grisha!
Carla caught the plague going around!
Can you help her?!
Put her in the rear bed.
Dr. Jaeger...
My parents... have it, too.
Don't worry, I'll help everyone.
Dr. Jaeger!
My wife is well again!
Dr. Jaeger, thank you!
Congrats!
You're appointed as the
Scout Regiment commander.
Congratulations!
Congratulations, Dr. Jaeger!
Shit, our base!
It's no use! Let's retreat, Commander!
The moron charges straight into death.
He's always the only one who lives.
I hear nobody on Erwin's
squad has died yet.
Wish they'd change commanders then.
Someone special...
A chosen one...
Keith?
Carla? Who's this child?
Eren. He's our boy.
I guess you never got the news.
My husband worried about you.
Yeah... I'm sorry.
Do you intend...
...on keeping this up until you die?
It's about time you...
Do you know why people live and
die without doing a damn thing?
It's because they lack imagination!
Their whole lives, for nothing!
They're not ashamed of a life
that produces nothing but shit!
They can't accomplish greatness... No!
They can't even understand it!
Not even the half of it!
So a girl who flirts with
every man in sight...
...good for absolutely nothing
besides pouring drinks...
...will never...
Yes...
Normal people accomplish nothing...
Erwin... Will you take over as commander?
Special people do exist.
This just means I was never one of them.
Why did I not realize that simple fact?
Wall Maria was destroyed!
Shiganshina District was decimated!
Us in Trost District are next!
Keith!
Oh... I know now...
It was your fault...
Eren.
Wake up, Eren. Was your
mother not with you?
Dad...
Mom...
A Titan...
...ate her.
Eren.
Avenge your mother.
You must.
I know you can.
Let's go.
Wait. Where are you going?
Don't follow us.
Wait.
Why don't you just do it? Avenge Carla...
Why? Is it because you're special?
Unlike me...
What if your kid is different, too?
He might not be a chosen one either.
Right?
Are you going to curse... someone else now?
This child is not like you.
He's my son.
I beg you.
Stay out of it.
Thunder?
And then I carried your unconscious
body back to the shelter.
That is everything I know.
So that's... it?
Now we know the real reason you resigned.
Not to atone for the soldiers you killed,
but because you realized
you were never special.
That's the childish reason you're here.
Quit it, Hange.
Screw your inferiority complex.
Don't run from reality.
Isn't that what vowing to give
our hearts was all about?!
Please stop, Hange.
The commandant was right.
I was never special or anything.
But...
I'm the son of a special man.
That's all it is.
Your mother...
Carla said this...
Is it wrong not to be special?
I don't think that way.
When it comes to my child...
...it's fine if he's never great.
He doesn't have to be better than anyone.
After all, just look at him...
He's so cute!
He's already special.
Because he was...
...born into this world.
And you, just like your father wanted...
...chose to set ablaze your life...
...which will burn to
ashes outside the walls.
In the end, I couldn't...
I couldn't change a single thing at all.
I'm a mere bystander.
The night before leaving for Shiganshina...
Now knowing of a world outside the walls,
with hope and fear in their hearts,
they pray for the future of humanity.
Next episode: "Night of the
Battle to Retake the Wall."
"Night of the Battle to Retake the Wall"